"It" departed for the south.
"Dia" berjalan ke arah selatan.
"It" collects information through stimulation.
Melalui stimulus "dia" mengumpulkan informasi.
And it is able to replicate and emulate them.
Lalu menirunya lewat informasi tersebut.
From a rock...
Dari batu...
to a wolf...
menjadi serigala.
and now, a human.
Lalu sekarang adalah manusia.
It had no characteristics of a human.
Dia tak punya kualitas sebagai manusia.
It was incontinent
Karena itu badannya jadi kotor.
and lacked a source of nutrition.
Dia tak mendapatkan nutrisi yang cukup.
As such,
Dengan segera...
it soon died.
dia pun mati.
Yet this was no issue.
Namun, bagi dirinya,
For this being, death is but a change of condition.
kematian hanyalah sebuah perubahan keadaan saja.
By now, it had already died six times.
Hingga kini, dia telah mati enam kali.
Yet its regeneration mechanics were functioning just fine.
Lalu kemampuan regenerasinya pun bekerja dengan baik.
The first time, it took all of five days before it came back to life.
Pertama kali untuk hidup kembali dia butuh lima hari.
By the sixth time, it took only 12 hours.
Sampai keenam kali, dia hanya butuh 12 jam.
Pain promotes growth.
Rasa sakit mempercepat regenerasinya.
There are no meaningless deaths.
Tak ada kematian yang sia-sia.
It died again.
Dia mati lagi.
Yet this was no issue.
Namun, itu bukan masalah.
TO YOUR ETERNITY
UNTUKMU YANG ABADI
Mom, I'm so hungry I feel like I'm going to die...
Ibu, aku sangat lapar.
Oh, poor Usatarou.
Usajiro, kau kasihan sekali.
Mom will make food for you!
Ibu buatkan makanan untukmu ya.
It's done! Eat up!
Sudah selesai! Cepat makanlah.
So good!
Enak sekali.
Mom's cooking is amazing!
Ibu hebat sekali!
As expected of Mom!
Makanannya sangat enak.
Oh, thank you!
Terima kasih.
With this, you are a proper adult.
Dengan begini, kau menjadi orang dewasa.
Thanks, Grandma.
Terima kasih, Nenek.
What are you looking at, March?
Kamu sedang lihat apa, March?
Look. What might this be?
Lihat, apa ini?
Were they born safely?
Kau yang melahirkannya?
Yes. Meet the sixth member of our family, Kanitarou!
Benar, ini adalah Kanitaro, bayi laki-laki yang keenam.
I had just been thinking we needed a child!
Baru saja aku ingin punya anak lagi.
With this, our family has eight people!
Dengan begini, jumlah keluargaku jadi delapan.
That's right.
Benar.
Dearest, a feast in thanks!
Suamiku, ini tanda terima kasihku. Ayo dimakan!
Oh, it looks so good!
Kelihatannya enak sekali.
The food you make is the best, after all.
Makananmu memang yang terenak.
Aren't you glad you married me?
Kau bahagia bukan menikah denganku?
It's time to eat, March.
March, waktunya makan.
Mom! Dad!
Ayah, Ibu.
Look! It's Kanitarou!
Kalian lihat, ini Kanitaro.
Oh, good work!
Mainan baru ya? Bagus sekali.
Sorry for troubling you all the time, Parona.
Parona, maaf selalu merepotkanmu untuk menjaganya.
Not at all.
Tak apa-apa.
I feel at ease playing with March.
Aku merasa tenang berada di dekatnya.
Mom...
Ibu.
When will March become an adult?
Kapan aku menjadi orang dewasa?
Are you asking that again?
Pertanyaan itu lagi?
As I've told you, you need to go to sleep without wetting the bed 3000 times in a row.
Tunggu kau tak ngompol dan tidur selama 3.000 hari lagi untuk menjadi dewasa.
I can't wait for that!
Aku tak bisa menunggu selama itu!
I want to grow up soon and become a mother!
Aku ingin cepat dewasa dan menjadi seorang Ibu.
Did you know
Apa kalian tahu?
Ri next door isn't a kid anymore?
Raisa, anak tetangga sebelah bukan anak-anak lagi.
She has already removed the paint on her face!
Tinta di wajahnya sudah dihapus.
The only kids left in this village
Anak-anak di dalam desa ini,
are me, Lisa, and that baby Lala!
hanya sisa aku, Risya dan Rara di sebelah.
It's embarrassing!
Memalukan sekali.
How about it, Lisa?
Bagaimana Risya?
Your big sister will feed you next time!
Lain kali biar Kakak yang menyusuimu saja.
Don't do that.
Jangan main-main lagi.
I'll teach you something nice, March.
March, aku beri tahu kabar baik untukmu.
If you aren't obedient, you won't become an adult.
Dengar, jika anak tak patuh, tak bisa menjadi dewasa.
Because adults are obedient.
Karena orang dewasa selalu patuh.
What is that supposed to mean? I don't get it.
Apa? Aku tak mengerti!
EPISODE TWO: A DISOBEDIENT GIRL
#2 GADIS YANG TAK PATUH
That bow is too heavy for you.
Busur itu terlalu berat bagimu.
Don't worry. You'll get good someday.
Tenang, suatu saat kau pasti menjadi mahir.
We'll help out, too.
Kami juga akan ikut membantu.
Let's all train hard together.
Mari berlatih bersama.
Thanks, everyone.
Terima kasih semuanya.
Where is Dad?
Di mana Ayah?
Dad is busy working today.
Ayah lagi bekerja.
But...
Namun...
You can't be selfish.
Jangan manja.
I wonder what that sound might be?
Suara apa itu?
No idea...
Tak tahu.
March.
March.
Big sister!
Kakak.
Where are we going?
Kita mau ke mana?
I found a really nice place.
Aku menemukan tempat yang bagus.
Let's go play there.
Jadi, hari ini kita main di sana.
What are you doing?
Apa yang kau lakukan?
She is a village girl, isn't she?
Dia adalah gadis desa, kan?
Did you not hear the order to assemble?
Apa kau tak mendengar panggilan untuk berkumpul?
Rejoice, all of you.
Semuanya, mari bersenang-senanglah.
This village was lucky to be selected this year.
Beruntung desa ini terpilih lagi tahun ini.
The ritual to thank the deity who blesses Ninannah with peace and prosperity,
Syukuran pada Dewa Oniguma yang memberi kedamaian dan kemakmuran
The Spirit Bear,
untuk wilayah Ninnana
shall occur in this village.
akan diadakan di sini.
We shall offer an unsullied girl to the Spirit Bear.
Kita akan memilih seorang gadis suci untuk dipersembahkan pada Dewa Oniguma.
The selection shall be carried out by us Yanome,
Menurut tradisi,
as dictated by tradition.
pemilihan dilakukan oleh kita, orang-orang Yanome.
Let's see.
Aku lihat dulu.
This child.
Aku pilih anak ini.
Congratulations, March!
Selamat, March!
Congratulations!
Selamat...
Thank you very much.
Terima kasih semuanya.
Congratulations?
Kenapa memberi selamat?
For what?
Apa yang terjadi?
You've been chosen for a very prestigious position, March.
Kau terpilih untuk melakukan hal yang mulia.
Prestigious?
Hal yang mulia...
We're sorry, March!
Maafkan kami, March!
W... What happened, Mom?
Ke... kenapa? Ibu?
You are to die,
Kau akan mati,
March.
Nona March.
For everyone's sake, you shall be the sacrificial lamb for the Spirit Bear.
Demi para penduduk, kau akan menjadi persembahan kita untuk Dewa Oniguma.
Sacrifice?
Persembahan?
I am Hayase of the Yanome.
Namaku Hayase.
I have been assigned to watch over March
Aku dapat perintah untuk menjaga Nona March,
until the completion of the ritual.
hingga ritualnya selesai.
Please stand down.
Mohon jaga jarak.
No men, even her father, may approach her.
Laki-laki tak diperbolehkan mendekati korban persembahan.
I must ensure that she remains pure.
Supaya dia tak ternodai.
Then, as for the ritual's schedule...
Sekarang, aku umumkan proses ritualnya.
A day before the departure,
Sehari sebelum keberangkatan,
a banquet will be held.
pada saat perjamuan di desa,
Families and friends may bid farewell to her.
silakan ucapkan selamat tinggal pada keluargamu hari ini.
Over the next three days, we shall climb the mountain.
Kemudian akan menghabiskan tiga hari untuk mendaki gunung.
We will escort her carefully,
Kami akan berhati-hati dalam perjalanan.
so have confidence that she will be safe.
Mohon kalian jangan khawatir.
We will have March rest on top of the altar.
Lalu Nona March akan dibaringkan di atas altar.
We shall return immediately without waiting for the Spirit Bear to descend.
Kami akan segera pergi sebelum Dewa Oniguma tiba.
If anything remains after a year, we shall collect it
Setelah setahun, kami akan kumpulkan yang tersisa di sana,
and return it to you.
mengembalikannya pada kedua orang tuanya.
March doesn't want to die.
March tak ingin mati.
Dying means that I won't become an adult, right?
Jika mati, tak bisa menjadi dewasa, kan?
Yes.
Benar.
So I don't want to die.
Jadi, aku tak ingin mati!
That's too bad.
Maaf, sangat disayangkan.
Why are you deciding everything for March?
Kenapa kau seenaknya buat keputusan untukku!
That's how it is.
Ini adalah aturan.
What is that supposed to mean?
Aku tak mengerti!
No! No! No! I don't want to die!
Tak mau... Aku tak mau mati.
Why do I have to die?
Kenapa harus aku yang mati?
Why is March the only one who can't grow up?
Kenapa hanya aku yang tak bisa menjadi dewasa?
Why...
Kenapa...
March!
March!
Be obedient.
Kau harus patuh.
-March, eat these. -These are for you, too.
-March, makanlah ini. -Ini juga.
Lala.
Rara.
March, I made this for you.
March, aku buatkan ini untukmu.
Wear it on your last day, all right?
Pakailah ini di hari terakhirmu, ya?
Thanks.
Terima kasih.
I'll do my best.
Aku akan berjuang.
Does your job also include watching me when I use the bathroom?
Apa tugasmu mengawasiku ke toilet?
I am ensuring that you stay safe until the final day.
Aku harus selalu waspada dan pastikan kau aman sampai akhir.
That's right. You need to make sure that I don't run away.
Kau mengawasiku supaya aku tak kabur, kan?
Let me give you a warning.
Aku beri kau peringatan.
If you run away,
Jika kau kabur,
Lala may be the one to die instead.
Rara akan menggantikanmu mati.
And if Lala runs away, too?
Jika Rara juga ikut kabur?
We'll take the kid who can't run away.
Jika begitu pilih anak lain yang tak kabur.
What's wrong?
Ada apa?
There, there...
Jangan menangis lagi.
You've done well, March.
Sampai hari ini, kau telah melakukan yang terbaik.
You've stayed obedient until now. Good job.
Kau sangat patuh. Bagus sekali.
There is a saying.
Ada legenda berkata begini.
The world beyond death is one of freedom.
Di alam setelah kematian, kau akan mendapat kebebasan.
You may do anything and become anything.
Bisa melakukan apa pun dan berubah jadi apa pun yang kau mau.
There you could be the adult you could not be here.
Di sana, kau bisa menjadi dewasa seperti yang kau inginkan.
An arrow...
Anak panah?
She ran away!
Dia kabur!
Wait...
Jangan kabur!
Ms. Hayase!
Tuan Hayase!
Go after March!
Cepat kejar March!
Don't let her get away!
Jangan biarkan dia kabur!
She's gone! Look over there!
Dia menghilang. Coba cari ke sana!
-She's not here! -Look harder!
-Tak ada. -Cari dengan cermat.
I'm sorry, Dad...
Maafkan aku, Ayah.
I couldn't be obedient...
March tak bisa menjadi anak yang patuh.
There she is!
Ketemu, itu March!
What is that?
Itu apa?
Wait for me!
Tunggu aku!
What...
Apa?
What is this thing?
Ini... apa?
Um...
Itu...
Where are you going?
Kau mau ke mana?
Take March with you.
Bawalah aku juga.
I see.
Ternyata begitu.
Did you intend to fake March's death with these?
Kau berniat memakai ini untuk memalsukan kematian March.
I've understood what you wanted to do.
Aku mengerti apa yang ingin kau lakukan.
Play pretend, it seems.
Namun, ini seperti memainkan sebuah drama.
Don't misunderstand.
Namun, jangan salah paham.
The one to punish you will not be me,
Bukan aku yang akan menghukummu.
but your own people of Ninannah.
Namun orang-orang Ninnana kalian.
Where is March?
Di mana March?
Um... Well...
Bukan... Itu...
Did she escape?
Dia berhasil lolos?
We should go back to the village and get another...
Kita kembali ke desa dan cari penggantinya saja.
Why do such a shameful thing when we could just find her?
Lebih baik menemukannya daripada melakukan hal yang memalukan.
We're going to go find her! Now!
Cepat pergi cari lagi!
No! Wait! There's a monster!
Tak bisa, tunggu! Di sana ada monster!
A monster?
Monster?
What are you?
Kau ini sebenarnya apa?
You looked like a pile of bones at first.
Awalnya kau hanya kerangka.
But then you wiggled around
Lalu bergerak sana sini,
and then you came back to life!
kemudian hidup kembali.
One time, my big sister stepped on a bug, but then it was still alive!
Sebelumnya ada seekor serangga mati diinjak Kakak, kemudian hidup lagi.
We were really surprised!
Itu membuat Kakak terkejut.
That's called...
Aku ingat saat kejadian itu...
Im... Imm...
Namanya a... abadi...
Immortal, right?
Abadi dan tak mati, kan?
That's what my big sister taught me.
Kakakku yang mengajariku.
By the way, where did you come from?
Oh iya, dari mana asalmu?
You're definitely not from Ninannah.
Seharusnya bukan orang Ninnana, kan?
You don't look like you're from Yanome, either.
Juga bukan orang Yanome.
What's your name?
Siapa namamu?
I'm March!
Namaku March.
Hey! Say something! Can't you speak?
Jawablah aku! Apa kau bisu?
Oh, that fruit looks sweet.
Buah itu terlihat manis.
I see. You must be hungry.
Ya, perutku juga lapar.
I'll get it.
Aku ambilkan untukmu.
Leave it to me. I'm good at climbing trees!
Serahkan padaku, aku pandai memanjat pohon.
Here.
Ini untukmu.
What? You can't be serious...
Yang benar saja?
You look so pitiful...
Kau kasihan sekali.
Did your parents never teach you?
Apa orang tuamu tak mendidikmu?
Here. You hold it with your hands and eat it.
Kau lihat, makan dengan tangan.
Hey! How could you?
Kenapa kau begitu?
Good grief.
Dasar.
That's not nice! That was March's share!
Jahat, itu yang mau March makan!
Stop it!
Menyebalkan.
No! These are March's!
Tak boleh, semua ini punyaku.
Did you want to eat that much?
Apa kau begitu ingin memakannya?
You see, when someone you don't know does nice things for you,
Dengar, jika ada orang asing baik padamu,
you have to say, "Thank you".
kau harus bilang "Terima kasih" padanya.
Can you say it? Here, "Thank you".
Ayo bilang "Terima kasih."
Thank... you...
Terima kasih.
Hey! Don't run off like that!
Tunggu! Jangan pergi begitu saja.
Are you sleeping?
Kau mau tidur?
Mom! Dad!
Ibu, Ayah.
March came back!
Aku pulang!
March!
March!
Huh? Where is Lisa?
Aneh, di mana Risya?
It's your fault, March.
Semua salahmu!
Big sister...
Kakak.
Because you ran away.
Karena kau kabur,
Two people became sacrifices.
mereka berdua jadi korban persembahan.
Oh? Why did you follow me?
Ada apa? Kenapa mengikutiku?
Goodness.
Dasar.
March is not your mom, you know?
Aku juga bukan Ibumu.
A boy who knows nothing...
Anak laki-laki yang tak mengerti apa-apa,
and March, a girl who wants to be a mother...
bersama dengan March berperan sebagai Ibu yang mencintai anak.
Their lives gradually began to intertwine.
Mereka mulai saling berkomunikasi.
Parona, who fights to save March's life,
Parona berjuang untuk menyelamatkan hidup March.
the persistent Hayase...
Hayase yang gigih,
and...
kemudian
"EPISODE THREE A MINOR EVOLUTION" a giant shadow that suddenly appears.
"#3 EVOLUSI KECIL" mendadak muncul bayangan yang besar.